And I think as we're experimenting with these possible robot futures, we actually end up learning a lot more about ourselves as opposed to just these machines. And what I learned that day
Je pense qu'en expérimentant ces futurs robotiques possibles, on finit par en apprendre plus sur nous-mêmes que juste sur les robots. J'ai appris, ce jour-là,
was that I had pretty high expectations for this little dude. He was not only supposed to be able to navigate the physical world, but also be able to navigate my social world -- he's in my space; it's a personal robot. wWhy didn't it understand me? My host explained to me, "Well, the robot is trying to get from point A to point B, and you were an obstacle in his way, so he had to replan his path, figure out where to go, and then get there some other way," which was actually not a very efficient thing to do. If that robot had figured out that I was a person, not a chair, and that I was willing to get out of its way if it was trying to get somewhere, then it actually would have been more efficient at getting its job done if it had bothered to notice that I was a human and that I have different affordances than things like chairs and walls do. You know, we tend to think of these robots as being from outer space and from the future and from science fiction, and while that could be true, I'd actually like to argue that robots are here today, and they live and work amongst us right now. These are two robots that live in my home.
que j'avais des attentes plutôt élevées pour ce petit gars. Il ne devait pas seulement pouvoir évoluer dans l'espace physique, mais aussi dans mon espace social – il en fait partie : c'est un robot personnel. Pourquoi ne me comprend-il pas? Mon hôte m'a expliqué : « Un robot essaie d'aller d'un point A vers un point B, tu étais un obstacle sur son chemin, il a donc dû reprogrammer son parcours, réfléchir où aller et ensuite s'y rendre autrement », ce qui n'était pas une façon de faire très efficace. Si ce robot avait réalisé que j'étais une personne, pas une chaise, que j'étais prête à m'écarter de son chemin, où qu'il ait cherché à aller, il aurait plus efficacement rempli sa mission, s'il avait détecté que j'étais humaine et que mes potentialités sont différentes des chaises et des murs. On pense souvent que ces robots viennent d'une autre planète, du futur, de la science-fiction. Et même si c'était vrai, j'aimerais soutenir qu'aujourd'hui, les robots existent, ils vivent et travaillent parmi nous. Voici deux robots qui vivent chez moi.
They vacuum the floors and they cut the grass every single day, which is more than I would do if I actually had time to do these tasks, and they probably do it better than I would, too. This one actually takes care of my kitty. Every single time he uses the box, it cleans it, which is not something I'm willing to do, and it actually makes his life better as well as mine. And while we call these robot products -- it's a "robot vacuum cleaner, it's a robot lawnmower, it's a robot littler box," I think there's actually a bunch of other robots hiding in plain sight that have just become so darn useful and so darn mundane that we call them things like, "dishwasher," right? They get new names. They don't get called robot anymore because they actually serve a purpose in our lives. Similarly, a thermostat, right? I know my robotics friends out there are probably cringing at me calling this a robot, but it has a goal. Its goal is to make my house 66 degrees Fahrenheit, and it senses the world. It knows it's a little bit cold, it makes a plan and then it acts on the physical world. It's robotics. Even if it might not look like Rosie the Robot, it's doing something that's really useful in my life so I don't have to take care
Ils passent l'aspirateur et coupent l'herbe, tous les jours, c'est plus que ce que je ferais, si j'avais le temps. Ils le font aussi probablement mieux que moi. Celui-ci s'occupe de mon chat. Chaque fois qu'il utilise son bac, il le nettoie, ce que je ne suis pas prête à faire, même si ça améliore beaucoup sa vie et la mienne. Comme on appelle ces robots des produits – « robot aspirateur », « robot tondeuse à gazon », « robot bac à litière » - je pense qu'il y a beaucoup d'autres robots cachés sous nos yeux, ils sont juste devenus tellement utiles et banals qu'on les appelle par exemple « lave-vaisselle ». Ils ont de nouveaux noms. On ne les appelle plus « robots » parce qu'ils ont une raison d'être dans nos vies. De même, un thermostat – je sais que mes amis roboticiens seront sans doute gênés que j'y voie un robot, mais il a un but. Son but est de faire en sorte que ma maison soit à 19 degrés, il sent ce qui l'entoure. Quand il fait un peu froid, il crée un programme et agit sur l'univers physique. C'est de la robotique. Même s'il ne ressemble pas à Rosie, le robot des Jetson, il accomplit quelque chose qui est très utile dans ma vie. Donc je n'ai plus besoin
of turning the temperature up and down myself. And I think these systems live and work amongst us now, and not only are these systems living amongst us but you are probably a robot operator, too. When you drive your car, it feels like you are operating machinery.
d'augmenter ou de baisser la température moi-même. Les robots vivent et travaillent parmi nous aujourd'hui, mais ils ne font pas que vivre parmi nous : vous êtes probablement vous aussi un opérateur de robot. Quand vous conduisez, c'est comme si vous pilotiez un engin.
You are also going from point A to point B, but your car probably has power steering, it probably has automatic braking systems, it might have an automatic transmission and maybe even adaptive cruise control. And while it might not be a fully autonomous car, it has bits of autonomy, and they're so useful and they make us drive safer, and we just sort of feel like they're invisible-in-use, right? So when you're driving your car, you should just feel like you're going from one place to another. It doesn't feel like it's this big thing that you have to deal with and operate and use these controls because we spent so long learning how to drive that they've become extensions of ourselves. When you park that car in that tight little garage space, you know where your corners are. And when you drive a rental car that maybe you haven't driven before,
Vous allez vous aussi d'un point A à un point B, mais vous avez sûrement une direction assistée, un système automatique de freins, peut-être une boîte automatique et même un régulateur de vitesse. Bien que votre voiture ne soit pas complètement autonome, elle l'est quand même un peu et c'est tellement utile, on peut conduire plus sûrement, on a juste l'impression que ça disparaît à l'usage, pas vrai ? Donc, en conduisant sa voiture, c'est juste comme aller d'un endroit à un autre. On n'a pas l'impression que c'est si compliqué à utiliser, toutes ces commandes. C'était si long d'apprendre à conduire qu'elles deviennent des extensions de nous-mêmes. Quand on gare sa voiture dans une place étroite, on sait où sont les côtés. Mais quand on loue une voiture, qu'on n'a peut-être jamais conduite,
it takes some time to get used to your new robot body. And this is also true for people who operate other types of robots, so I'd like to share with you a few stories about that. Dealing with the problem of remote collaboration. So, at Willow Garage I had a coworker named Dallas, and Dallas looked like this. He worked from his home in Indiana in our company in California. He was a voice in a box on the table in most of our meetings, which was kind of OK except that, you know, if we had a really heated debate and we didn't like what he was saying, we might just hang up on him. (Laughter) Then we might have a meeting after that meeting and actually make the decisions in the hallway afterwards when he wasn't there anymore. So that wasn't so great for him. And as a robotics company at Willow, we had some extra robot body parts laying around, so Dallas and his buddy Curt put together this thing, which looks kind of like Skype on a stick on wheels, which seems like a techy, silly toy, but really it's probably one of the most powerful tools that I've seen ever made for remote collaboration. So now, if I didn't answer Dallas' email question, he could literally roll into my office, block my doorway and ask me the question again -- (Laughter) until I answered it. And I'm not going to turn him off, right? That's kind of rude. Not only was it good for these one-on-one communications, but also for just showing up at the company all-hands meeting. Getting your butt in that chair and showing people that you're present and committed to your project is a big deal and can help remote collaboration a ton. We saw this over the period of months and then years, not only at our company but at others, too. The best thing that can happen with these systems is that it starts to feel like you're just there. It's just you, it's just your body, and so people actually start to give these things personal space. So when you're having a stand-up meeting, people will stand around the space just as they would if you were there in person. That's great until there's breakdowns and it's not. People, when they first see these robots, are like, "Wow, where's the components? There must be a camera over there," and they start poking your face.
on prend du temps à s'habituer à notre nouveau corps robotique. C'est aussi vrai pour les gens qui utilisent d'autres types de robots et je voudrais vous partager quelques expériences. À propos du travail à distance. A Willow Garage, mon collègue Dallas ressemblait à ça. Il travaillait pour notre entreprise californienne, de chez lui dans l'Indiana. C'était une voix au micro pendant la plupart de nos réunions, et ça marchait plutôt bien, sauf quand on avait un débat animé, qu'on n'était pas d'accord avec lui, on pouvait juste raccrocher. (Rires) Ensuite on pouvait avoir une autre réunion et prendre les décisions dans le couloir, quand il n'était plus là. Ce n'était pas super pour lui. Comme on est fabricants de robots, on avait quelques morceaux en trop qui traînaient, alors Dallas et son ami Curt ont fabriqué ça : une sorte de Skype fixé sur un bâton équipé de roues, qui ressemble à un jouet geek idiot, mais, en vrai, c'est un des outils les plus puissants que j'aie jamais vus pour travailler à distance. Maintenant, si je ne réponds pas à la question de Dallas par mail, il peut littéralement rouler vers mon bureau, bloquer ma porte et me reposer la question – (Rires) jusqu'à ce que je réponde. Je ne vais pas le désactiver, ce serait impoli. Ce robot ne lui sert pas que pour les discussions à deux, mais aussi à être visible à la réunion des employés. Se caler sur une chaise, montrer aux gens que vous êtes là, engagé dans votre projet, c'est important et ça peut booster le travail à distance. On a pu le voir pendant des mois, puis des années, pas que dans notre entreprise, ailleurs aussi. Ce qui peut arriver de mieux avec un robot, c'est de sentir ne faire qu'un avec lui. C'est juste vous, votre corps et les gens commencent à lui reconnaître une existence propre. Donc, quand il y aura une réunion debout, les gens se placeront autour de lui comme ils l'auraient fait si vous étiez là. C'est génial, jusqu'à ce qu'il y ait des bugs. La première fois qu'ils voient ces robots, les gens cherchent les composants : « Il doit y avoir une caméra par ici », ils tapotent votre tête :
"You're talking too softly, I'm going to turn up your volume," which is like having a coworker walk up to you and say, "You're speaking too softly, I'm going to turn up your face." That's awkward and not OK, and so we end up having to build these new social norms around using these systems. Similarly, as you start feeling like it's your body, you start noticing things like, "Oh, my robot is kind of short." Dallas would say things to me -- he was six-foot tall -- and we would take him via robot to cocktail parties and things like that,
« Tu parles trop bas, je vais augmenter ton volume. » C'est comme si un collègue venait chez vous et disait : « Tu parles trop bas, je vais monter le son de ta tête. » C'est gênant et incorrect, on a donc dû créer de nouvelles normes sociales pour utiliser ces systèmes. De même, dès qu'on commence à s'y sentir comme dans son propre corps, on se met à remarquer des choses comme : « Mon robot est trop petit. » Si Dallas me parlait – il fait 1 mètre 80 – qu'on emmenait son robot à des cocktails et à des soirées,
as you do, and the robot was about five-foot-tall, which is close to my height. And he would tell me, "You know, people are not really looking at me. I feel like I'm just looking at this sea of shoulders, and it's just -- we need a taller robot." And I told him, "Um, no. You get to walk in my shoes for today. You get to see what it's like to be on the shorter end of the spectrum." And he actually ended up building a lot of empathy for that experience, which was kind of great. So when he'd come visit in person, he no longer stood over me as he was talking to me, he would sit down and talk to me eye to eye, which was kind of a beautiful thing. So we actually decided to look at this in the laboratory and see what others kinds of differences things like robot height would make. And so half of the people in our study used a shorter robot, half of the people in our study used a taller robot and we actually found that the exact same person who has the exact same body and says the exact same things as someone, is more persuasive and perceived as being more credible if they're in a taller robot form. It makes no rational sense, but that's why we study psychology. And really, you know, the way that Cliff Nass would put this
où on va, et que le robot fait 1 mètre 50, ce qui est proche de ma taille, Dallas me dirait : « Les gens ne me regardent pas vraiment. J'ai l'impression de ne voir qu'une mer d'épaules – il me faut un robot plus grand. » Je lui ai répondu : « Euh, non. Tu vas te sentir à ma place aujourd'hui. Tu vas voir ce que ça fait d'être au niveau de l'épaule des gens. » Cette expérience lui a fait ressentir beaucoup d'empathie, c'était plutôt formidable. Quand il venait lui-même me voir, il ne restait plus debout, devant moi, à me parler, il s'asseyait et me parlait à mon niveau, c'était très touchant. On a donc décidé d'étudier ce phénomène en laboratoire, de voir ce que des différences, comme la taille d'un robot, changent. La moitié de notre échantillon a utilisé un petit robot, l'autre moitié, un grand robot. On a découvert que la même personne, avec exactement le même physique et qui dit exactement la même chose, est plus convaincante et paraît plus crédible avec la grande version du robot. Ce n'est pas rationnel, d'où le recours à la psychologie. En fait, Cliff Nass dirait
is that we're having to deal with these new technologies despite the fact that we have very old brains. Human psychology is not changing at the same speed that tech is and so we're always playing catch-up, trying to make sense of this world where these autonomous things are running around. Usually, things that talk are people, not machines, right? And so we breathe a lot of meaning into things like just height of a machine, not a person, and attribute that to the person using the system. You know, this, I think, is really important when you're thinking about robotics. It's not so much about reinventing humans, it's more about figuring out how we extend ourselves, right? And we end up using things in ways that are sort of surprising. So these guys can't play pool because the robots don't have arms, but they can heckle the guys who are playing pool and that can be an important thing for team bonding, which is kind of neat. People who get really good at operating these systems will even do things like make up new games, like robot soccer in the middle of the night, pushing the trash cans around. But not everyone's good. A lot of people have trouble operating these systems. This is actually a guy who logged into the robot and his eyeball was turned 90 degrees to the left. He didn't know that, so he ended up just bashing around the office, running into people's desks, getting super embarrassed, laughing about it -- his volume was way too high. And this guy here in the image is telling me, "We need a robot mute button." And by that what he really meant was we don't want it to be so disruptive. So as a robotics company, we added some obstacle avoidance to the system.
qu'il nous faut interagir avec ces nouvelles technologies, malgré le fait que nous ayons de très vieux cerveaux. La psychologie humaine n'évolue pas aussi vite que la tech, on se met tout le temps à jour, pour chercher du sens dans un monde où les machines autonomes nous entourent. Normalement ce sont les gens qui parlent, pas les machines. Et donc on associe beaucoup de choses comme la taille d'une machine – pas de la personne – à celui qui utilise le système. Je pense que c'est très important quand on réfléchit à la robotique. Ce n'est pas tant réinventer l'humain, mais plutôt découvrir comment étendre ses possibilités. On en vient à utiliser les robots d'une façon très surprenante. Ces robots ne peuvent pas jouer au billard car ils n'ont pas de bras, mais ils peuvent interpeller les joueurs, ce qui peut beaucoup contribuer à créer un esprit d'équipe, c'est assez génial. Les gens qui arrivent très bien à utiliser les robots inventent même de nouveaux jeux, comme le football robotique en pleine nuit, renversant les poubelles. Tout le monde n'y arrive pas. Beaucoup de gens ont du mal à utiliser les robots. Cet homme s'est connecté à un robot, dont l'œil était tourné à 90 degrés sur la gauche. Il ne le savait pas et il s'est mis à se cogner partout au bureau, à foncer dans les gens, qui devenaient très gênés. Il en riait – son volume était bien trop fort. Cet homme me disait sur l'image : « Il faut un bouton pour couper le son. » En fait, il voulait dire qu'on ne veut pas de robots aussi turbulents. En tant que fabricants de robots, on a intégré au système des obstacles à éviter.
It got a little laser range finder that could see the obstacles, and if I as a robot operator try to say, run into a chair, it wouldn't let me, it would just plan a path around, which seems like a good idea. People did hit fewer obstacles using that system, obviously, but actually, for some of the people, it took them a lot longer to get through our obstacle course, and we wanted to know why. It turns out that there's this important human dimension -- a personality dimension called locus of control, and people who have a strong internal locus of control, they need to be the masters of their own destiny -- really don't like giving up control to an autonomous system -- so much so that they will fight the autonomy;
Il a reçu un petit laser pour détecter les obstacles. Si l'opérateur du robot essaie de le faire aller dans une chaise, ça ne marchera pas : le robot en fera juste le tour, ce qui est une meilleure idée. Grâce à ce programme, les gens heurtaient moins d'obstacles, mais quelques personnes mettaient plus de temps à finir la classe d'obstacles, on a voulu savoir pourquoi. Il s'est avéré qu'il y a un élément important chez l'humain : le locus de contrôle, rattaché à la personnalité. Les gens dotés d'un fort locus interne de contrôle ont besoin de maîtriser leur propre destin – ils détestent laisser le contrôle à un système autonome. Ils se battent contre ce système autonome :
"If I want to hit that chair, I'm going to hit that chair." And so they would actually suffer from having that autonomous assistance, which is an important thing for us to know as we're building increasingly autonomous, say, cars, right? How are different people going to grapple with that loss of control? It's going to be different depending on human dimensions. We can't treat humans as if we're just one monolithic thing. We vary by personality, by culture, we even vary by emotional state moment to moment, and being able to design these systems, these human-robot interaction systems, we need to take into account the human dimensions, not just the technological ones. Along with a sense of control also comes a sense of responsibility. And if you were a robot operator using one of these systems, this is what the interface would look like. It looks a little bit like a video game, which can be good because that's very familiar to people, but it can also be bad because it makes people feel like it's a video game. We had a bunch of kids over at Stanford play with the system and drive the robot around our office in Menlo Park, and the kids started saying things like, "10 points if you hit that guy over there. 20 points for that one." And they would chase them down the hallway. (Laughter) I told them, "Um, those are real people. They're actually going to bleed and feel pain if you hit them." And they'd be like, "OK, got it." But five minutes later, they would be like, "20 points for that guy over there, he just looks like he needs to get hit." It's a little bit like "Ender's Game," right?
« Si je veux heurter cette chaise, je le ferai. » Ils n'apprécient pas d'avoir une aide programmée, c'est une chose importante à savoir alors qu'on construit des voitures de plus en plus autonomes, non ? Comment réagiront des gens différents face à cette perte de contrôle ? Ce sera différent selon les caractéristiques de chacun. On ne peut pas traiter les humains comme s'ils étaient semblables. On diffère par notre personnalité, notre culture, parfois même, en fonction de notre état émotionnel. Pour concevoir des systèmes d'interactions entre humains et robots, on doit prendre en compte les caractéristiques humaines, pas que celles de la technologie. Avec le sens du contrôle vient le sens des responsabilités. Si vous pilotiez un robot utilisant un de ces systèmes, voilà ce à quoi l'interface ressemblerait. C'est un peu comme dans un jeu vidéo : c'est bien, car c'est très familier pour les gens. Mais le mauvais côté, c'est que les gens se croient dans un jeu vidéo. Des enfants sont venus jouer avec le système à Stanford, conduire un robot dans nos bureaux à Menlo Park et ils se sont mis à dire, par exemple : « 10 points si tu cognes le type là-bas, 20 points pour l'autre ». Ils poursuivaient les gens dans le hall. (Rires) Je leur ai dit : « Ce sont de vrais gens qui vont vraiment saigner et avoir mal si vous les cognez. » Ils répondaient : « OK, compris. » Mais cinq minutes plus tard, c'était : « 20 points pour le type là-bas, il a l'air d'avoir besoin d'être cogné. » Un peu comme dans La Stratégie Ender.
There is a real world on that other side and I think it's our responsibility as people designing these interfaces to help people remember that there's real consequences to their actions and to feel a sense of responsibility when they're operating these increasingly autonomous things. These are kind of a great example of experimenting with one possible robotic future, and I think it's pretty cool that we can extend ourselves and learn about the ways that we extend ourselves into these machines while at the same time being able to express our humanity and our personality. We also build empathy for others in terms of being shorter, taller, faster, slower, and maybe even armless, which is kind of neat. We also build empathy for the robots themselves. This is one of my favorite robots. It's called the Tweenbot. And this guy has a little flag that says, "I'm trying to get to this intersection in Manhattan," and it's cute and rolls forward, that's it. It doesn't know how to build a map, it doesn't know how to see the world, it just asks for help. The nice thing about people is that it can actually depend upon the kindness of strangers. It did make it across the park to the other side of Manhattan -- which is pretty great -- just because people would pick it up and point it in the right direction. (Laughter) And that's great, right? We're trying to build this human-robot world in which we can coexist and collaborate with one another, and we don't need to be fully autonomous and just do things on our own. We actually do things together. And to make that happen, we actually need help from people like the artists and the designers, the policy makers, the legal scholars, psychologists, sociologists, anthropologists -- we need more perspectives in the room if we're going to do the thing that Stu Card says we should do, which is invent the future that we actually want to live in. And I think we can continue to experiment with these different robotic futures together, and in doing so, we will end up learning a lot more about ourselves. Thank you. (Applause)
Il y a un monde réel de l'autre côté, je pense que c'est notre responsabilité, en créant ces interfaces, d'aider à se souvenir que nos actions ont des conséquences réelles, à avoir le sens des responsabilités quand on utilise ces systèmes de plus en plus autonomes. Voici de très bons exemples d'expérimentations d'un futur robotique possible. Je pense que c'est formidable de pouvoir étendre ses possibilités, d'apprendre de notre façon de le faire, dans ces machines, tout en étant capable d'exprimer son humanité et sa personnalité. Et on a de l'empathie pour autrui quelle que soit sa taille, sa vitesse et parfois même son handicap, c'est génial. On a aussi de l'empathie pour les robots eux-mêmes. Voici un de mes robots préférés. C'est le Tweenbot. Ce petit gars a un fanion qui dit : « J'essaie d'aller à ce croisement à Manhattan », il est mignon, il roule, et c'est tout. Il ne sait pas comment créer une carte, ni voir le monde : il demande de l'aide. Ce qui est bien chez les gens, c'est qu'il a pu compter sur la gentillesse d'étrangers. Il a bien traversé le parc jusqu'à l'autre côté de Manhattan – ce qui est génial – juste parce que les gens le mettaient dans la bonne direction. (Rires) Et c'est génial, non ? On cherche à construire ce monde mixte humain et robotique dans lequel on peut coexister et travailler, tous ensemble. Pas besoin d'être complètement autonome et de tout faire tout seul. On fait les choses ensemble. Et pour y arriver, on a besoin de l'aide des artistes et designers, dirigeants politiques, juristes, psychologues, sociologues, anthropologues, etc. On a besoin de plus de points de vue si on veut faire ce que Stuart Card nous conseille : inventer le futur dans lequel on veut vraiment vivre. Je pense qu'on peut continuer à expérimenter différents futurs robotiques ensemble, et, ce faisant, on finira par en apprendre beaucoup plus sur nous-mêmes. Merci. (Applaudissements)